Cian White

The Owl.

Grand Canal Dock, Dublin 2, Dublin, Ireland

Phone: +353 87 315 6535

ciwhite@tcd.ie

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie at the intersection of people and nature. I am interested in how an understanding of ecological systems can inform management for ecosystem service provision to create Nature-based Solutions. I have worked closely with plant-pollinator systems in wildflower meadows to understand how meadow characteristics impact a variety of ecosystem services. My experience interviewing meadow users has recently sparked an interest in understanding how both ecology and psychology influence the outcome of interactions between people and nature. I am particularly interested in understanding how to create meaningful interactions that result in improvements in wellbeing. Understanding the aspects of nature that contribute to meaningful interactions will be useful for designing ecological systems to maximize wellbeing benefits, while understanding how an individual's orientation, their cognitive, affective and behavioural state, influence the creation of meaningful interactions is important for recommending how to most beneficially interact with nature. Ultimately, I hope that research into meaningful interactions with nature results in Nature-based Solutions to stress and anxiety, combats the extinction of experience phenomenon and boosts the conservation of biodiversity.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Ecology, Trinity College Dublin, Current

Concentrations: Nature-based Solutions, Ecosystem Services, Plant Animal Interactions, Network Ecology.

Provisional Dissertation Title: Connecting Nature: plant-pollinator interactions, ecosystem services and Nature-based Solutions.

Dissertation Advisors: Jane Stout, Ph.D., Marcus Collier, Ph.D.

B.A, Zoology, Trinity College Dublin, Dublin, 2017

Dissertation: Exploring the population dynamics of three contrasting populations of Plantago lanceolata; an investigation into intra specific variation.

Dissertation Advisor: Yvonne M. Buckley, Ph.D.

First Class Honours, 73% overall grade. 4th Position in Class.

PUBLICATIONS

No papers published yet but below is a selection of manuscripts in various stages of progress.

Primary Authorship Manuscripts

White, C., Collier, M., Stout, J. C. "A framework for identifying Nature-based Solutions". *In submission with Ecosystem Services*.

White, C., Collier, M., Stout, J. C. "Synergies of cultural and regulating ecosystem services from urban wildflower meadows: implications for management" *Analysis to be finalized*.

White, C., Collier, M., Stout, J. C. "The beta-diversity of interactions in human dominated landscapes: effects of landscape type and intensity" *Analysis to be finalized*.

Co-authorship Manuscripts

Russo, L., Fitzpatrick, U., Larkin, M., Mullen, S., Power, E., Stanley, D., White, C. Stout, J. "Agriculture defaunates plant-pollinator networks". *In submission with Nature.*

Ross, S. R. J., Arnoldi, J. -F., Jackson, A., White, C., Stout, J., Donohue, I. "Complexity increases the sensitivity of ecosystem functioning". *Final Draft*.

Csergő, A. M., Healy, K., Baudraz, M. E. A., Kelly, D., Kelly, R., O'Connell, D., Ó Marcaigh, F., Smith, A. L., Villellas, J., White, C., Wilson, J., Yang, Q., Buckley, Y. M. "A meta-analysis of mainland and island populations suggests a general isolation syndrome affecting traits, demography and genetic diversity." *Final Draft*.

PRESENTATIONS

White, Cian (2018). "What is a Nature-based Solution" presented at the Environ Conference at Cork Institute of Technology

White, Cian (2018). "Impact of Human Disturbance on Plant Pollinator Interactions" presented at Scandinavian Association for Pollination Ecology (SCAPE), at Blessington, Ireland.

White, Cian (2018). "Interaction Networks are Impacted by Landscape Type, but not land use intensity" presented at British Ecological Society's annual meeting in Birmingham, UK.

White, Cian (2019). "Managing Wildflower Meadows for Multiple Ecosystem Services" presented at Scandinavian Association for Pollination Ecology (SCAPE), at Huur, Sweden.

White, Cian (2019). "Redefining Nature-based Solutions" presented at British Ecological Society's annual meeting in Belfast, NI.

White, Cian (2020). "Does Floral Abundance or Diversity of Wildflower Meadows Correlate with Self-Reported Wellbeing" presented at Irish Pollinator Research Network, Maynooth, Ireland.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant and Lecturer, Trinity College Dublin, 2017- Current

Teaching Assistant Courses: Introduction to Statistics, Plant Animal Interactions, Fundamentals of Ecology.

Lecturer: Ecology and Society

Head NERD, Trinity College Dublin, 2018 - 2019

The NERD club is a weekly gathering of researches with an interest in ecology and evolution to discuss ideas and present projects. I organized and ran the club for a year.

Supervisor of Undergraduate Research Projects, Trinity College Dublin, 2018 - Current

Co-supervisor of undergraduate student in 18/19 academic year. Student was awarded best thesis.

Co-supervising three undergraduate projects in 19/20 academic year.

GRANTS AND FELLOWSHIPS

Trinity Award (Trinity College Dublin Research Grant, 2017)

WORKSHOPS

Winter Workshop on Complex Systems 2020 in Lausanne, Switzerland.

AWARDS AND HONORS

Best Overall Oral Presentation, Environ 2018

Best 5 Minute Talk, SCAPE 2018

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

British Ecological Society Irish Ecological Association

RELEVANT SKILLS

Good knowledge of R statistical program and Arc GIS mapping software.